Finding Aid for Letters, Documents, & Other Manuscripts, Duane Norman Diedrich Collection, 1595-2007
William L. Clements Library, University of Michigan
- Letters, Documents, and Other Manuscripts, Duane Norman Diedrich Collection, 1595-2007
  - 1945 [ca. April-May]. Pat[rick] L. Ash AMsS to Edith L. Gingrich; s.l., 10 pages; 2nd Bn. 14th Marines, H. and S. Bty., 4th Marine Division. History of the 4th Marine Division, noting its service in the Marshall Islands, Saipan, Tinian, and Iwo Jima. Vividly describes his experiences at Iwo Jima, including the initial landing and first night on the island. "... one would never suspect that on this tiny island of volcanic ash was soon to be fought the bloodiest battle of the entire war and the hardest fight in the one hundred and sixty nine years of the United States Marine Corps." Attributes survival to God.
  - 1945 May 14. "Frank" [Francis Guiffrida] ALS to Walter Bielefield; Okinawa, [Japan], 2 pages; Lt. Commander Francis Guiffrida, H&S Co., Medical Battalion, 1st Marine Division. Sending a Japanese infantry manual and a Japanese 31 caliber rifle: "I'm not going to be so generous with that because it is the only one I have and they are not easy to get. Some men out here pay a tremendous price for them." Would like Walt to hold it for him until he returns. Describes the condition of the rifle and advice on ammunition. The battle [of Okinawa] is still "raging furiously." "When you see Marine die - and especially when among them are your friends, the smallest battle gains much importance." On American Red Cross stationery.
  - 1945 May 16. "Joe" [Joseph May] Swing TLS to Beverly [F. Brown]; [Philippines], 1 page; Headquarters, 11th Airborne Division. References Beverly's note to "Look" about a "filthy thing they had about George Patton." "After 101 days straight of killing Japs, with an average of 93.8 per day, on the 102d day we failed to bag any game, so far as we are concerned, at an end." Attended a fiesta in San Juan, "in honor of one of the companies that liberated the town." A rest camp has been formed "on the beach near Lemery." Misses baseball. Will head to Mindoro for quail hunting. "Big things are evidently being cooked up by all the brass hats, but none of it trickles down to the lower levels, so we just sit, wait, and see what is going to happen." See also: Joe Swing TLS to Beverly and Louise Brown dated February 23, 1942.
  - 1945 September 24. Dwight [D. Eisenhower] TNS; Cy to Arthur Eisenhower; s.l., 2 pages [total]; Enclosing a TL from Dwight Eisenhower to C.H. McClean. Written on Headquarters, U. S. Forces, European Theater, Office of the Commanding General stationery. Includes a typed copy of the letter, thanking McClean, of the Graybar Electric Company, for providing an electric fan for Eisenhower's mother. "...there is nothing more dear to me than the comfort and wellbeing of my Mother. Anyone who is nice to her has placed me everlastingly in his debt." Arthur has told him that McClean has a son in the 42nd Division.
  - 1948 September 26. Earl [Eisenhower] ALS to Arthur [B. Eisenhower]; s.l., 1 page; Letter concerning the upcoming inauguration of Dwight D. Eisenhower as president of Columbia University. Received a belated invitation. Notes no effort to attend the inauguration of Milton as President of Kansas State, "and, out side of the fact that Columbia is larger than Kansas State, I see no difference in their position."
  - 1951 January 3. Dwight D. Eisenhower TLS to Arthur B. Eisenhower; s.l., 1 page; Letter written regarding the transfer of $10,000.00 of Dwight Eisenhower's funds from Arthur Eisenhower's bank to the Dupont Circle Bank in Washington D.C. Signed both "Ike" and "Dwight D. Eisenhower." On D.D.E. personal stationery, featuring five stars.
  - 1953 September 19. W[illiam] C. Handy TLS to Bob Whittemore; New York, New York, 3 pages; Recording of Handy's address at the University of Michigan will be broadcast over "500 Radio Stations through the Field of Education." Handy discusses the influence music has and how orders for their music are coming in from distant places. Political campaigns in New York: "one of our racial group will more than likely be elected to an important office for the first time, and yet, I fall back on an oft repeated quotation, 'I care not who makes the Nation's laws if I can write the Nation's songs.'" Discusses the state of the music publishing business. Article by Arno L. Bader, English professor at the University of Michigan, on "The Memphis Blues." Mentions his father's objections to studying music, but the state of the nation prevented him from attending Wilberforce University for Theology. Received an honorary Doctorate of Music from Wilberforce. "We publish much Sacred music written by more than 50 Race composers and about as many of the other racial group and this letter is my request to be permitted to send you sample copies that your Minister of Music could look over for its inclusion in your churches." Has received letters from "Senators, Congressmen, Governors, Mayors, ex-Presidents, and Generals of the front rank." Describes several of his compositions, inspirations, and honors bestowed upon him. On Handy Brothers Music Co., Inc. stationery.
  - 1956 July 30 [approved]. Dwight Eisenhower Printed DS to [Duane N. Diedrich]; [Washington, D.C.], 1 page; Public Law 851 - 84th Congress. H.J. Res. 396. Joint resolution to establish "In God We Trust" as the national motto of the United States. Signed by Dwight Eisenhower, 1960. With: Whitman, Ann C. 1908-1991 TLS to D. N. Diedrich; Washington D.C., 1p. May 14, 1960. Whitman informs Diedrich that the President signed the copy of Public Law 851 and that she is returning it with his best wishes. On White House stationery. With: 3 newspaper clippings: Two regarding the national motto, 1956. One regarding Ann Whitman.
  - 1958 January 3. Herbert [Hoover] TLS to Neil MacNeil; New York, New York, 1 page; Regarding a speech to be given at Valley Forge on Washington's birthday, for the Freedoms Foundation. Would like MacNeil to read the opening paragraph and the final paragraph. "If I don't do this I simply can not take the time to prepare a speech, and I don't want to either." On Hoover's personal stationery.
  - 1958 April 2. Walt Disney TLS to Dr. Robert A. Reid; s.l., 1 page; Refuses a request for a speaking engagement. "It is not my practice to accept speaking engagements because I do not consider myself a speaker and furthermore, time is not available for such activities because of the pressure of production and business affairs." On Walt Disney's personal stationery.
  - 1961 June. André Maurois AMsS; [France], 2 pages; Written in French, includes typescript but no translation. Maurois describes a French press luncheon with President John F. Kennedy. Comments on journalists' difficult questions, touching on matters in France, the Soviet Union, England, and the United States. Admires Kennedy's diplomatic answers and poise. Describes Kennedy's tactics and the importance of strong oratory skills. References Abraham Lincoln's Gettysburg Address. Includes the 1961 June 2 issue of France-Soir (8pp), featuring a picture of John F. Kennedy and Jackie Kennedy Onassis. (Box 11)
  - [1964] December 2. Darryl F[rancis] Zanuck TLS to Elmo Williams; s.l., 8 pages; Zanuck summarizes recent conferences in Paris and their importance to his studio (20th Century Fox). Remarks on the studio's finances and the upcoming 1965 production year: 13 "important" films at a cost of $46,650,000. Detailed comments on the production of: Fantastic Voyage, Do Not Disturb, Our Man Flint, Flight of the Phoenix, The Day Custer Fell, The Sand Pebbles, Call Me When the Cross Turns Over, and others. Mentions Salvador Dali, Honor Blackman, Doris Day, Rod Taylor, James Stewart, Audrey Hepburn, Charlton Heston, Burt Lancaster, Brigitte Bardot, Steve McQueen, Sean Connery, and others. "We have learned today that even good pictures do not do business if they do not have that added touch or that added "gimmick", or if they do not have that certain something that will pull in an audience."
  - 1965 June 22. Dwight D. Eisenhower TLS to Lou Cohen; Gettysburg, Pennsylvania, 1 page; Unable to give a speech for Cohen's United Nations committee. "I have been advised by my doctors to begin cutting down drastically on my out-of-town engagements, particularly when they involve ceremonies requiring a speech from me. I have promised both the doctors and my family to observe their instructions..." Applauds the United Nations. Offers possibilities for other speakers, including Richard Nixon, [George W.] Romney, [Mark O.] Hatfield, and [William] Scranton. On DDE Gettysburg Pennsylvania 17325 stationery (raised gold lettering).
  - 1969 January 31. Arthur [Rubinstein] ALS to Muriel and George Marek; [New York City, New York], 2 pages; Rubinstein thanks the Mareks for his birthday present: volumes of Liszt-Wagner correspondence, in which he was surprised to find two autograph letters by Liszt and Wagner. "And so - let me rethank you from the bottom of my heart for the regal gift!" On Rubinstein's personal stationery.
  - [1972 May, delivered]. Eugene McCarthy AMsS; s.l., 3 pages; McCarthy's notes for a speech delivered to the Commonwealth Club in San Francisco. References literature, Ayn Rand, politics, Vietnam and the military, courts, Congress, and presidential powers. NOTE: McCarthy unsuccessfully ran for the Democratic nomination for President of the United States in 1968, 1972, and 1992.
  - 1973 February 13. Karen Carpenter and Richard Carpenter TDS to Ars Nova, Inc.; [California], 7 pages; Ars Nova, Inc., employment contract for performances by "The Carpenters." Compensation: 15% of the total receipts or $150,000.
  - 1975 January 13. W[illia]m M. Rumpeltes TLS to Buddie Nicholas; Grand Island, Nebraska, 2 pages [total]; Sending a copy of the original message he recorded from Marshall Foch while acting as the first class wireless operator on the U.S.S. Utah. Comments on other services performed by the Utah and his current health. Written on the back of a photocopy of the Naval Signal sent by Marshall Foch on November 11, 1918. "Marshall Foch to Commander in Chief - Hostilities will cease upon the whole front from the eleventh November eleven o'clock (French o'clock) The Allied troops will not cross until a further order the line reached on that date and that hour."
  - 1988 June 13. John [F.] Kennedy Partially printed DS to Manatt, Phelps, Rothenberg, & Phillips; [Los Angeles, California], 1 page; Employment application for summer clerk position at the law firm of Manatt, Phelps, Rothenberg, & Phillips. Lists Mrs. J. Onassis as his emergency contact.
  - 2007 May 19 [delivered]. [Barack Obama] Typed speech; s.l., 6 pages; Typed printed speech, with manuscript corrections by Senator Barack Obama. "Remarks of Senator Obama, Southern New Hampshire University Commencement, Manchester, New Hampshire, Saturday, May 19, 2007." Comments on maturity and how it is reflected in politics and media. Challenges cynicism and calls on graduates to be active citizens. Discusses how he learned that "the world doesn't just revolve around you" and the problem with the "empathy deficit." Describes his decision to organize in Chicago and the need to challenge one's self. Emphasizes the need for perseverance. "Cultivating empathy, challenging yourself, persevering in the face of adversity -- these are qualities that dare us to put away childish things." Notes the power of American youth to enact change.
  - [no year] July 6. Josiah Quincy ALS to John Pierce; Cambridge, [Massachusetts], 1 page; Requests Pierce to call a meeting of the Board of Overseers to be held in Quincy's council chambers. Needs to discuss conferring honorary degrees [likely from Harvard University].
  - [no year] September 9. Adele Douglas (Mrs. Stephen Douglas) ALS to Mother [Ellen O'Neale Cutts]; St. Louis, [Missouri], 1 page; Travelling with Mr. Douglas and will be heading south. Fatigued. "... he wanted me so much I consented to go & I do not find any moment to breathe."
  - Undated. He[nr]y R. Bishop ALS, 1 page; "I have occasion for four (single) orders for the Oratorio of Tomorrow night: and also, two single for Saturday night!"
  - Undated. D[aniel?] Dulany ALS; s.l., 1 page; Regarding the sale of pig iron.
  - [no year] January 28-30. Newbold H. Trotter Partially printed Invitation to Ferd[inan]d J. Dreer; Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], 1 page; Invitation for viewing of new painting, "Children of the Tropics"
  - Undated. ADf; s.l., 23 pages; Manuscript [draft?] of "Origin & History of Corporations." Describes the evolution of corporate history and law in Rome, Greece, and Europe. Discusses the "different species of Corporation and their several characteristics." Notes "the authority by which Corporations may be established," commenting on English and American law.
  - [no year] July 24. A[rabelle] G[riffith] W[harton] ALS to T[homas] I. Wharton; Long Branch, New Jersey, 2 pages; Comments on summer resort activities. Has been feeling unwell, "either the air or the bathing or something has been too stimulating for me." Encourages him to visit rather than "remain over those tough old parchments."
  - Undated. W[illia]m Craik ALS to William Campbell, 3 pages; Answering Campbell's inquires about Colonel Mercer's "Conduct during the last session of the General Assembly of Maryland." Uncertain about the reliability of his memory, but comments on Mercer's actions concerning taxes, finances, and questioning the "sale of confiscated British Property subsequent to the treaty."
  - Undated. Sam[ue]l Miller ALS to Rev. [Archibald?] Alexander; s.l., 1 page; Feeling unwell and will be unable to attend the Board of Missions meeting. Would like Alexander to inform them.
  - Undated. Geo[rge] Catlin ANS to Mr. Mitchell, 1 page; Order for printing.
  - Undated. Jo[seph] Wood ANS to [Anson Dickinson]; [Washington, D.C.], 1 page; Poem inviting Dickinson to visit.
  - Undated. D[aniel] Huntington ALS to T. Addison Richards; s.l., 2 pages; Congratulations to Mr. Richards for his being elected to an artists academy. Assures Richards that his acceptance was based on "your own abilities and marked improvement in landscape."
  - Undated. John L. Hall DS to H[ubbard] Grave; s.l., 1 page; Payment on chairs, table, washstand and bedstead. Recipient recorded as H. Graves.
  - October 25. W[illia]m H. Denny ALS to Richard Denny; Mocksville, Davie County, North Carolina, 3 pages; Comments on setting up his medical practice and tending to another doctor who fell ill with a fever. Region experiencing an uncommonly sickly season, which has impacted the capacity for the courts to function. Notes the high death toll. A local preacher "said that he had preached 1. and two funeral sermons every day for 3. weeks and that the people had become used to the toll of the bell so as not to mind it." Mentions medicines.
  - Undated. Amelia Bingham ALS to Mr. Jordan; Cincinnati, [Ohio], 2 pages; Is busy rehearsing every day, but if the recipient will send for her at the Opera House, she will "run away from my people for an hour or so." On St. Nicholas Hotel stationery.
  - Undated. Joseph Lancaster ALS to J. Webster; [Newburgh, New York?], 3 pages; Returning several books. Instructions for printing and payment of handbills and advertisements for lectures Lancaster intends to deliver in the area around Newburgh. Addressed to J. Webster, Webster & Skinner.
  - Undated. George Bancroft ALS to Reverend W. Ware; s.l., 1 page; Letter of apology stating that he is unable to write anything substantial until his volume is published.
  - Undated. J. Gates ALS to J.M. Carlisle; s.l., 1 page; Forwarding packages for Carlisle to distribute to their appropriate recipients.
  - Undated. T[homas] DeWitt Talmage AMsS; [New York, New York?], 2 pages; Quips on ideal womanhood and the character of women. "Fashioned to refine & soothe & lift & irradiate home & society & the world."
  - Undated. S[abine] Baring-Gould AMsS; s.l., 1 page; Manuscript copy of "Onward Christian Soldiers," signed by Sabine Baring-Gould (1834-1924). Housed in individual custom box.
  - Undated. D[aniel] Webster ALS to R[obert] C. Winthrop; [Boston, Massachusetts], 2 pages; Regarding the unpleasant speaking conditions at Faneuil Hall. Will not return until the problems are fixed.
  - Undated. Robert Owen Signature; s.l., 1 page; Cut cover: Robert Owen's signature, written on paper headed with printed text "Robert Owen's Millennial Gazette. Registeredfor Foreign Transmission." Addressed to "The Assistant Post Master General of the United States."
  - Undated. Franklin Pierce ALS to Jeanie [Jane Pierce]; Concord, [New Hampshire], 2 pages; Plans to travel to Hillsboro. "If my interests there were in as satisfactory condition as I find them here, there would be nothing to annoy me." Attended a lecture by [John B.] Gough at Phoenix Hall on "street life in London." Entertaining, but "did not amount to much in the way of instruction." Will return on Saturday and bring clothing articles that he is "so prone to scatter about."
  - Undated. D[wight] L. Moody ALS to Dr. Seamour; s.l., 2 pages; Mr. Jacob will take charge of the choir. Questions regarding the size of the hall. Inquires about the location of the day meeting.
  - Undated. Phil Shea ALS to Julia Shea; [France], 1 page; Picture postcard, "Les Ruins de Clermont-en-Argonne." "... the war is about over if not at an end all ready." From "musician Phil Shea U.S. Army." Includes censor stamp. See also Phil Shea ALS to Julie Shea, March 19, 1919.
  - [World War I era]. 5 envelopes, Two envelopes from Lieutenant V. R. Modruff (21st Field Artillery, 5th Division Regiment, A.E.F.). Two envelopes to N. E. Dutro at Camp Bowie, Texas. One envelope from Private Leslie Henderson (Engineers, A.E.F.).
  - ca. 1880s?. S. D. Loring Printed Pamphlet; Boston, [Massachusetts], 17 pages; Some Facts Regarding Water Works Bonds as a Desirable Form of Investment with Statistics "Prepared by S.D. Loring, Dealer in Investment Securities." Promotes investment in water works, comparing them to riskier investments. Notes the public health and safety advanced by water works. Comments on methods of supply, and discusses the British water works as an example. Includes a table of United States towns, organized by population, showing "Receipts and Expenditures of some Leading Water Works."
  - Undated. Alben W[illiam] Barkley Signed photograph; s.l., 1 page; International News Photo of Barkley standing, with gavel. Signed "Sincerely Alben W. Barkley"
  - Undated. Irving Berlin AQS; s.l., 1 page; Signed, "Alexanderly yours."
  - Undated. W[illiam] H[oward] T[aft] ANS to [ ]; s.l., 1 page; "File these papers left me...for use in connection with my political speech and also my annual message - WHT."
  - Undated. Theodore Roosevelt TMs; s.l., 4 pages; Typed draft of a section from the second chapter in Theodore Roosevelt's autobiography, including redacted portions and revisions which appear in the printed edition. Discusses his speech "The Strenuous Life," and translations of it into Chinese and Italian. Comments on types of success, coming from unique abilities of the exceptional man and from dedication and perseverance. "I need hardly say that all the success I have ever won have been of the second type. I never won anything without hard labor and the exercise of my best judgment and careful planning and working long in advance."
  - Undated. Photograph, 1 page; Carte de visite photograph of Henry Ward Beecher (1813-1887), mounted on paper printed with his name and Brooklyn, N.Y.
  - Undated. [Randolph Caldecott] Illustration; s.l., 3 pages (total); Three pencil and ink drawings of rural life. [NOTE: Originals located in the Graphics Division].
  - Undated [ca. 1930s?]. [Walt Disney Productions] Film Cell; s.l., 1 page; Hand-painted film cell of Happy from Walt Disney's "Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs." Original located in the Graphics Division.
  - Undated. Theodore Roosevelt AQS; s.l., 1 page; "With warm regards to a fellow Republican and lover of American history."
  - Undated. AMs; [Boone County, Indiana], 12 pages; Address of a teacher at the Indiana Sugar Plain school, as he departs "its chair as Teacher." Notes significance of education and the duties of children and parents. Proper education assures a better future for all. Role of family, schools, community, religion, and the press. Applauds Quakers' dedication to education but underscores the need for a broader public school system. Disputes the notion that Jesus' apostles were unlearned. Comments on the difficulties facing Quaker boarding schools and the Sugar Plain school, including irregular attendance and poor behavior. Includes unattributed selections from Charles Northend's The Teacher and the Parent; a Treatise upon Common-School Education.
  - [no year] August 11. Emily Wharton ALS to T[homas] I. Wharton; Long Branch, [New Jersey], 3 pages; Describes resort activities, including attending a small fair with fireworks and a tableaux. Comments on her tableau, "a scene from the Tempest where Miranda is discovered playing chess with Ferdinand."
In addition to this collection of individual letters, documents, and other manuscripts, the Duane Norman Diedrich Collection includes a variety of other archives and manuscripts, which have their own catalog records. Please search the finding aids or Library catalog for "Duane Norman Diedrich Collection" to identify them.
Schopieray, Cheney J. One Hundred Selections from the Duane Norman Diedrich Collection of Manuscript Americana, 17th-20th Century. Ann Arbor, Mich.: William L. Clements Library, 2018.